Guide to the Stanford Technology Ventures Program, Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders Seminar, Videorecordings SC1209
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings, 2001-2014
  - Levinson, Frank, How Does Going Public Change You and Your Company?, 2001-10-31; 673; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Inevitably, when a company goes public, there's an enormous amount of change that takes place, says Levinson. While the IPO may be an indication of financial success, the true measure is within the company, and maintaining a level of normalcy and maintaing the company's original culture, he adds.
  - Levinson, Frank, Envisioning The Future For Optics, 2001-10-31; 674; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Levinson believes leadership skills are vital in maintaining a successful company. These skills include being able to see into the future, and predict where the company should go. He talks about the possible future of Finisar.
  - Levinson, Frank, Changing Finisar Technology and Business Practices, 2001-10-31; 675; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    As a company grows and develops, it is possible that its methods for design and production change, says Levinson. The company may also look to new avenues of possible innovations. He describes the changes Finisar has seen over the years.
  - Levinson, Frank, Importance of Family In Building a Start-up, 2001-10-31; 676; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    When starting a company, it's important to tell your family that they'll rarely see you, says Levinson, and to tell them how important they are to the whole process. The stress involved with a startup is often mind-boggling, and the support of family can be the saving grace, he adds.
  - Levinson, Frank, Managing The Leverage of Customer Input on Product Development, 2001-10-31; 677; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Clearly, without producing something that meets a customer's needs, says Levinson, a business is not a good position to succeed. However, it's important that the business create its own goals and work to fulfill its own needs as well. He describes the best methods to reaching a compromise in this situation.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Career Development, 2001-10-03; 678; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley, David, founder and CEO of IDEO Product Development, grew up in Ohio, where he survived on a diet of Velveeta cheese and white bread, He attended Carnegie Mellon and studied electrical engineering, but spent more time working on carnival floats. After graduation, he worked for Boeing on the 747. He learned early that in a large company, he didn't get to choose the people he worked with. He came to the Graduate Product Design Program at Stanford, where he discovered his passion--design. His first company was called the Intergalactic Destruction Company. One of the things he learned in graduate school was that you can use design in any situation in life.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Building a personal Gratification Company, 2001-10-03; 679; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley explains that he has a unique perspective on starting companies--his goal is not growth, but to create a personal gratification system. A place where he can work with friends. He explaines that many of his comments on starting a company may not apply to companies that are trying to grow as fast as possible.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Follow Your Passion, 2001-10-03; 680; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley describes three important steps in starting a company: 1) Follow your passion 2) Hire great people 3) Focus on process. His passion is design, but there must be a balance between passion and business issues. People often worry too much about the financial side of the company and fail on the emotional side of the company, he says.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Design is Risk-Taking, 2001-10-03; 681; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley further describes his passion and what design means to him. He describes design as a process of having a combination of ideas in the head that need to be organized, while making a leap of faith about how it will be presented. It is a totally enjoyable experience, he says, there's a zen moment where time goes by and you lose track of everything. He presents a few design projects, including personal Sky, SpyFish and weather-related inventions.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Hire Great People, 2001-10-03; 682; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    IDEO Founder Kelley, David suggests avoiding conventional approaches to hiring employees and building teams. In this clip, Kelley offers a few suggestions: 1) Hire individuals or non-confomists to stimulate the organization, 2) Hire a diverse range of experts and generalists from different fields, and 3) Form "hot groups" of 8-12 people for maximum impact. Kelley also encourages building close ties to universities to source potential staff. To Kelley, an ideal hire interacts well with established staff and demonstrates an "attitude of wisdom" that strikes a balance between the ability to promote ideas and the ability to consider feedback.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, The Process of Design, 2001-10-03; 683; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley believes that you need a language, a process and a framework in order to design. He stresses that experience is key success factor: learn from all the projects you've worked on, distil the knowledge and apply it to your future projects. He recommends reading The Art of Innovation for IDEO's concept of a great process.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Product Development Process: Observation, 2001-10-03; 684; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley talks about how the observation phase is the most overlooked part of the development process. Kelley hires social scientists to watch people complete tasks instead of asking them usability questions. He prefers to see them as customers instead of users and strongly believes that customer satisfaction comes with understanding their values. He gives examples of how his team will observe a customer in their usual environment instead of inviting them into a sterile lab for product testing. The case studies he presents include a television remote control.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Designing Products vs Designing Experiences, 2001-10-03; 685; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley believes you start to think about things completely different when you think your job is to design the experience of using the device as opposed to designing the device itself. Kelley feels that to captivate an audience you need to build a context around the technology you are marketing and take into consideration how outside factors will affect how your product is perceived. He uses methods of transportation as an example
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Design as an Iterative Process, 2001-10-03; 686; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley believes that how quickly you create an initial prototype is directly proportional to how successful a product will be. Essentially, given a set project deadline, the earlier you invite feedback, the more chances you have to revise and improve. He calls this "enlightened trial and error."
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Prototyping the Mouse, 2001-10-03; 687; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley narrates his experience prototyping the Apple and the Microsoft mice.
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, Career Advice, 2001-10-03; 688; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Follow your passion, hire great people, and focus on process, says Kelley
  - Kelley, David, 1951-, How do you pick clients?, 2001-10-03; 689; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kelley begins by joking that in current times, an individual or business that shows up with the promise of cash is a customer of IDEO. He recounts a previous client categorization schematic IDEO employed to color-code their clients. He also emphasises the importance of taking on balanced projects which pay well, are innovative and of interest to his designers.
  - Earl, Nick, Organizational Structure: General Manager at EA, 2003-11-12; 714; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl, Nick, General Manager of Electronic Arts Redwood Shores Studio, talks about how the General Manager's job is to run one of EA's six studios, which are the places where they actually build the product. The GM administers and manages the portfolio of products at the site. Each product is then run by an executive producer. The executive producers are entrepreneurs in their own right and the products are managed almost like independent ventures.
  - Earl, Nick, Allocating capital for new products, 2003-11-12; 715; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl talks about how the majority of the products at EA are sequels that are released every year. The main decision for EA on these projects is budgeting how many people to work on each every year, he says. Occasionally, there is a new product idea. This idea must pass a lot of market opportunity analysis before it is launched because it is very expensive and risky to build a new product. Still, new products are seen as a critical part of the future of the company, he adds.
  - Earl, Nick, The Entrepreneur in the Game Industry, 2003-11-12; 716; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    According to Arcadia Kim, Chief Operating Officer for Electronic Arts Los Angeles, an entrepreneur is someone who sees an opportunity that other people cannot see, tries to understand the competitive landscape around this opportunity, assumes the inherent risk, and relentlessly and persistently pursues success. Specifically in the game industry, however, the objective for the entrepreneur is to deliver fun, she adds.
  - Earl, Nick, Game Development Process, 2003-11-12; 717; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim explains that EA's strategy is based on nailing down the "X," or organic fun concept for that product. EA shares knowledge across studios and around development creating a collaborative environment. The development process is pretty standard: build prototypes, do market tests, start to build it and, ultimately, finalize the product, she says.
  - Earl, Nick, Intellectual Property, 2003-11-12; 718; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim talks about how there is a large range in the projects at EA. Team sizes range from 30 people to 200. Development times take 10 months to 2-3 years. Some projects are original licensed intellectual property, like Lord of the Rings; others are hybrid intellectual property, like Golden Eye, based off of James Bond. Some games at EA are developed completely internally, others are partly outsourced to third party companies, and some are the result of partnerships.
  - Earl, Nick, Market potential: GameBoy, 2003-11-12; 719; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Erin Turner, a producer at Electronic Arts specializing in action-hero titles, explains that the GameBoy has a pretty substantial market with 40 million sold worldwide. The mission with the GameBoy is to create some unique draw or additional fun factor, since it does not have nearly the graphical capabilities as a console, she says. The team's challenge is to provide the optimal gaming experience, while working within the constraints of the limited hardware.
  - Earl, Nick, Positioning: James Bond and GameBoy, 2003-11-12; 720; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    There were a number of creative imperatives that were addressed in the development of James Bond, says Turner, primarily, retaining authenticity to the Bond character. Bond has an aura of always being in control of his environment, and this had to be maintained in the game. At a practical level, this required integrating combat and stealth in moment-to-moment game play. This was achieved by combining the best features of two competitive products, she adds.
  - Earl, Nick, Team Size and Product Development, 2003-11-12; 721; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Turner explains that while console teams can be upwards of 100 people, GameBoy games can be built with 10-15 people. This core group of people is divided up into engineering, art, animation, game design, and production. The product cycle was optimized to get the best product out as quickly as possible by condensing the concept cycle, focusing on a target, and rapidly incorporating feedback, she says.
  - Earl, Nick, Lessons Learned: Game Development, 2003-11-12; 722; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Turner talks about lessons learned in game development. The first lesson, she says, is that the product is only as good as the people that build it. The second lesson is to be a customer. In order to create a good product, she notes, the team was using the product everyday. The last lesson is to know when to add more features and when to cut and ship the product.
  - Earl, Nick, Organizational Structure: Directors vs. producers at EA, 2003-11-12; 723; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim talks about how producers have the creative vision for a product, while directors make sure the resources are properly allocated and the game ships on time. These are basically flipped from the roles of movie directors and producers, she adds.
  - Earl, Nick, Career Development: Going in circles until you come home, 2003-11-12; 724; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim describes her own path into game development at EA. She majored in film making as an undergraduate, started working in management consulting, and then decided to start a web-design company. Afterward she acquired an MBA and joined a startup company. Later on, she joined EA online in an entry-level position.
  - Earl, Nick, Seeing Failure as Opportunity, 2003-11-12; 725; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim's first game experience was a hugely successful online parlor game that was launched on AOL. Majestic, her second game, tried to stretch the Internet experience into the next generation of games, but didn't do as well, she says. The core team from Majestic was out of work and looking for another project, and stumbled into the Lord of the Rings.
  - Kim, Arcadia, Opportunity Assessment: Lord of the Rings, 2003-11-12; 726; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim talks about how in November 2001, the value proposition for Lord of the Rings was mixed. There was no movie yet and movie producer Peter Jackson had a questionable record. There was a lot of uncertainty over the successful prospect of the movies. However, the core team took an entrepreneurial attitude and decided to see what they could make of the opportunity.
  - Kim, Arcadia, Opportunity Assessment: Two Towers, 2003-11-12; 727; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim explains that the Two Towers development was done with a team of 40 at EA and the help of a third party developer in order to get it finished in time. The EA team injected their values, processes, management style and work ethic into the outside team, she says.
  - Earl, Nick, Opportunity Assessment: Return of the King, 2003-11-12; 728; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    he goal from the outset with Return of the King, says Kim, was to turn it into a perennial business. The "X" for Two Towers was "play the movie," but Return of the King was "live the movie." The development was brought in-house. Fan feedback was incorporated. The game was done in 16 languages for X-Box, Playstation2, GameBoy Advance, Nintendo GameCube, and the PC.
  - Earl, Nick, Lessons Learned: Game Development, 2003-11-12; 729; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kim talks about lessons learned in game development. The first lesson is to focus. You can't build a game unless you know what it is, she says. The second lesson is that with an enormous team, team culture is an issue. EA solved this by dividing the teams into smaller pods with their own leadership, she notes. The pod leaders would all coordinate on reaching milestones.
  - Earl, Nick, Game Design: James Bond, 2003-11-12; 730; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Turner talks about how the James Bond character was done in the third person in the game and his style and control comes from the mechanics of how he moves. He is always the master of his environment, she says.
  - Earl, Nick, Competition, 2003-11-12; 731; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl and Kim respond to the question: How has the competition from Grand Theft Auto influenced EA? Vice City is brilliant in its open world design, says Earl, you can go in any direction and interact with the environment. Grand Theft Auto was a little bit of a wake up call for EA suggesting that they should be doing something like it and watching out for the competition, he adds.
  - Earl, Nick, Innovation and Growth Post-IPO, 2003-11-12; 732; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl and Kim respond to the question: How do you increase innovation when a lot of the game development relies on established brands and sequels? A lot of efforts are going onto create new intellectual property, says Earl. Though risky, the new products will ultimately be the core component of the company's future.
  - Earl, Nick, Making an Interactive Game Successful, 2003-11-12; 733; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl talks about how EA is good at figuring out early on if a game is not going to be successful and starting over before it is too late. EA brings a compliment of distribution, marketing, resources, larger teams, better technology, and high caliber designers, artists, and engineers to help increase the chances of creating a successful game, he says.
  - Earl, Nick, Flexibility: Recognizing Growth Sectors, 2003-11-12; 734; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl explains that EA was previously focused mainly on sports games, but they found that they could not grow fast enough without expanding into other areas, namely entertainment. Games are continually becoming more mainstream and a lot of people can relate to movies making them a popular choice a game topic, he says. EA is now divided into three brands, EA Big (sports), EA Games, and EA Online.
  - Earl, Nick, The Future of Online Games, 2003-11-12; 735; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    The PC market has not been growing as much as was hoped, says Earl. Creating games that can be played against other players from a TV set is an important goal, but the commercial side about how to make money is still under development.
  - Earl, Nick, The EA Creative Process, 2003-11-12; 736; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Earl and Kim respond to the question: How do you manage the business imperatives versus the creative imperatives when developing a game? The decision makers at EA are people who really understand the creative side and have generally worked on the production side as well, says Earl, and are therefore able to make more informed decisions.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Introduction to Hummer Winblad and Mobius Venture Capital, 2004-02-25; 788; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad, Ann, co-founding Partner of Hummer Winblad Venture Partners, introduces herself and venture capitalist Heidi Roizen, who was not able to be there. She says that now is a very exciting time for entrepreneurship because there are lots of holes to fill in the software market and in the business landscape. She explains the founding and progress of Hummer Winblad Venture Partners and Mobius Venture Capital.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Drivers for Software Innovation, 2004-02-25; 789; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad, Ann of Hummer Winblad Ventures argues that there has been a steady dealflow in venture capital from 2002-2004. The software sector is still the big leader, though biotech is catching up. Though she doesn't discuss outsourcing, Winblad emphasizes that a company must consider where they can get the best intellectual capital. Today, company strategy starts globally. She also discusses trends in the software market, including open source material, Moore's Law (storage is free) and Metcalf's Law, and mergers and acquisitions.
  - Winblad, Ann L., How Consumer Markets and Enterprise Markets Drive the Software Industry, 2004-02-25; 790; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad talks about how the market is driven by consumers who want connectivity across devices, customizable products, and fair prices. Communication and collaboration are key to delivering the product the consumers want, she notes. The pricing structure cannot just be made up -- a company must demonstrate they can deliver undeniable short-term return on investment to the customer in order to justify the price.
  - Winblad, Ann L., 2004: Start of an Era of Optimism, 2004-02-25; 792; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad talks about how in 2001, there was a challenge finding consumers for software products and costs had to be cut. Now, demand is improving and CIO's are looking for larger revenue opportunities, she says.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Trends in Seed and Series A Investing, 2004-02-25; 793; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad explains that very few Series A investments were done in 2002. However, a lot more were done in 2003 and will be done in 2004, she says. The reasons for the decline since 2000 include: restart dollars were competing with the A round dollars; corporate investors disappeared (excpet Intel); and individual investing declined. Additionally, during this era, VCs were doing deals individually, creating twice as many A round deals and putting only one person on the board. Now, A round deals are syndicated to provide more coaching, she adds.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Hummer Winblad's and Softbank's Recent Investments, 2004-02-25; 794; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hummer Winblad is focused on enterprise, says Winbland, and Softbank on the consumer segment. Hummer Winblad's investments include: Voltage, the BASES contest winner in 2002, in security and reliability; Cenzic, in applications security space; two blade server companies, Scalent and Jareva; Knowmadic, in application integration; and Bridgestream, in provision and identity management. Softbank's projects include: Planitax, MessageCast, Castbridge, AuctionDrop, Perpetual Entertainment, and Reactrix.
  - Winblad, Ann L., VC Words of Wisdom for Entrepreneurs, 2004-02-25; 795; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    According to Winblad, the intellectual capital in your company and the coaching it gets is more important than money. There is a high bar for hiring employees. Most companies die of self-inflicted wounds rather than from competition or lack of opportunity, she says.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Keep Testing Your Core Assumptions, 2004-02-25; 796; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad, Ann advises entrepreneurs to boil down their business plan and tell everyone in the company the top five assumptions for success. "As time goes on, turn the assumptions into facts," says Winblad. She also reminds entrepreneurs to constantly reevaluate these assumptions as their company moves forward.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Outsourcing Software Development to Asia, 2004-02-25; 797; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad talks about how whole projects are not outsourced. The core technology is separated and written, while incremental pieces that would be done linearly are outsourced abroad. There are a lot of talented architects and developers around the world, she notes, but they do not have the vision to be inventors.
  - Winblad, Ann L., Customers are Key, 2004-02-25; 798; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Winblad talks about how VCs spend a lot of time with the leaders of major technology companies to find out what they are looking for. It is important to talk to consumers early rather than late, she notes. Today's leaders are technologically-savvy, know what they need, and are willing to tell you if you ask, she adds.
  - Winblad, Ann L., The Economic Context in 2004, 2004-02-25; 799; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    According to Winblad, M&A is picking up because companies now feel they can take risks in working with younger companies. Major corporations also went through a period of downsizing, but are now adding, she notes.
  - Winblad, Ann L., The Java Standard (and Competing Technology Standards), 2004-02-25; 800; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)